<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The jovial tinker of England: willing to hammer the Covenant and Scots commissioners into English. And to mend the breaches, and stop the holes of the Crowne of England, (miserably torne and bruised, both within and without) with the best mettle he can get. And at a very reasonable rate. Provided, he be not compelled to take the Scots sense upon the Covenant. He will rather walk about the countries, &amp; cry: Have you any work for a joviall tinker. / By Borialis guard.</title>
            <author>Borialis, Guard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E424_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864024</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864024</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116243</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116243)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 67:E424[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The jovial tinker of England: willing to hammer the Covenant and Scots commissioners into English. And to mend the breaches, and stop the holes of the Crowne of England, (miserably torne and bruised, both within and without) with the best mettle he can get. And at a very reasonable rate. Provided, he be not compelled to take the Scots sense upon the Covenant. He will rather walk about the countries, &amp; cry: Have you any work for a joviall tinker. / By Borialis guard.</title>
                  <author>Borialis, Guard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Hickman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Borialis, Guard is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 31"; the 8 in imprint date crossed out and date altered to 1647.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116243:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE JOVIALL TINKER OF ENGLAND: Willing To Hammer the Covenant and Scots Commiſſioners into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>AND To mend the breaches, and ſtop the holes of the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> (miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly torne and bruiſed, both within and without) with the beſt Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle he can get. <hi>And at a very reaſonable Rate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PROVIDED, He be not compelled to take the Scots Senſe upon the COVENANT. He will rather walk about the <hi>Countries,</hi> &amp; cry: Have you any work for a <hi>Joviall Tinker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By BORIALIS <hi>Guard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>John Hickman,</hi> 1648.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:116243:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116243:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Scotch Commiſsioners,</hi> tranſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Engliſh, for better underſtanding.</head>
            <p>ENGLAND is unhappily become the Tennis-ball of miſ-fortune, betwixt a Scottiſh King, and the Kingdom of Scots, Epitomiz'd in thoſe State-Merchants their Commiſſioners. The one ſtriving for an abſolute ſeparate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, the other for a joynt. A deſigne in practiſe ever ſince King <hi>James</hi> firſt ſet foot over <hi>Tweed.</hi> wherewith he traveld all his life, but wanting the Midwiſery of a Covenant, to bring it to paſſe; but now we are ſhared out by the Meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones of mutuall agreement betwixt His Majeſty and His Native Subjects, who formerly promiſed them three Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but that not contenting them, he hath now undertaken for the whole kingdome, to let them play the beſt of their Game, and they to him for the Crown to make it Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent (wheras the Identity and ſelf-ſameneſſe of intereſt ought to be 'twixt him and his People, as betwixt the head and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy naturall) and certainly the cards play faire for them, by the Cavaliers on the one ſide, and the Londoners on the other, the one ſworn ſlaves to Prerogative, and the other (for the moſt part) to the Scotch gloſſe upon the Engliſh Covenant, who long to feaſt the Mayor of Edenborough at Guild-hall. For the Scots finding the waters troubled, and humors ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, they think now is the beſt fiſhing, and the fitteſt time to work their ends, and therefore Print their papers in ſpite of the Parliament (in hope therby to ſet <hi>England</hi> on fire that they may come to warme their hands at it) a practiſe never known
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116243:3"/>
in uſe by any Miniſters of State but theſe, nor by them in no place in the world but here, becauſe their warpe is weaving in our Looms. They find the <hi>Round heads</hi> á ſtiffe people not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent, but reſolved to the death, to maintaine entire both the freedom &amp; intereſt of <hi>England</hi> without mixture or thraldom, therfore, <hi>Acheronta movebunt,</hi> they now renounce brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and contrary to Covenant fawne upon the Principles of the <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> face about to the common Enemy, towards whom throughout all theſe wars they carried themſelves ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inoffenſively, doing them no more hurt than what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily conduced to their owne particular advantage, in taking a few northern frontier Garriſons, and knowing them to bee moſtly prophane <hi>Eſaus,</hi> a people not much conſiderate of their owne concernments, they hope to buy out their birth-rights with a meſſe of pottage, and yet the Cavaliers hate a Round head, he cannot lightly love a Blew-cap, ſo that they may perchance find it prove the onely ſtay, to part two fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſtiffes is to turn a Beare looſe upon them both. And as for the <hi>Londoners,</hi> they are ſo confident of them, as alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy they call <hi>London</hi> (where their Papers of the diſpoſall of the Kings perſon was printed) <hi>Edenbrough,</hi> upon the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpiece therof, nor is it improper for the Metropolis to change her name, when the Kingdome changes her intereſt.</p>
            <p>And which is the worſt part of machiavell they make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion even <hi>The ſolemn League and Covenant</hi> to father all their baſtards, for my owne part I am one that have taken it, and wiſh all did ſo that will make conſcience to keep it, but cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be that Engliſh-man that takes it with the Scotch corrupt paraphraſe of a joynt intereſt, which <hi>ipſo facto</hi> renders him perjured as to the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> &amp; <hi>Supremacy,</hi> inhibiting all Engliſh-men to betray or communicate their publique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt (eſpecially legiſlative) to forraigne States, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it were the Covenant were neither given nor taken, then
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116243:3"/>
preſſed in policy as it is by the <hi>Scots,</hi> to hand-faſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> men in a joynt intereſt and propriety, or taken with perjury, as it is by the Cavaliers, who make no conſcience in ſwearing, nor for-ſwearing. But we now plainly ſee what were our brethrens ends in their firſt propounding this Covenant, not Religion and Conſcience, but Deſigne and Incroachment. I dare not judge ſo undivinely of their Divines who I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident had honeſter purpoſes, but whatſoever was their divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in it, their equity is ſtarke naught, the Commander in cheife whereof in his tranſactions here in <hi>England</hi> hath car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelfe extreame immorally, to the ſcandal of <hi>Presbytery</hi> and meriting the ſtoole of repentance, and yet it cannot bee denied but that what he hath done, hath been equitable, for the King raiſing him, by I know not what myſtery of State, from his deep diſpleaſure, to that height of Honour, can hee doe too much for ſuch a Maſter? that not onely forgave him, but gave him; Who is their main pillar of policy, and ſtrikes the greateſt ſtroak in this maſter-piece of tranſmigration of intereſt, and like Chancery Bills, affirms any thing, but proves nothing in his papers, knowing that a bad cauſe is better maintained by a brazen face, (bold aſſertions) than iron argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Therfore they never offer to reply, ſave with a deaf ear to the Houſe of Commons Anſwer to their papers, touching the diſpoſall of the King in <hi>England,</hi> wherby is made evident, that neither as to that particular, nor any thing elſe, either in, or relating to the Covenant, they have any right or intereſt to order or diſpoſe thereof by any joynt or united property.</p>
            <p>The words of the Covenant being expreſſe and clear to the contrary, in every Article of it, engaging both each Nation and each perſon, <hi>To endevour</hi> (both one thing and other) <hi>in our ſeverall places and callings—in our ſeverall Vocations—and according to our places and intereſts.</hi> So that though the Covenant by theſe definit expreſſions purpoſely provide againſt confuſion of Intereſts, that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116243:4"/>
being ſeverall diſtinct kingdomes, and each one onely to act in his ſeverall place; Vocation, calling and intereſt, yet without replying to theſe reaſons brought againſt their indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect quoting the Covenant in abſtract Poſitions thereby to compaſſe their end of joynt intereſt; they ſtill perſiſt from this Covenant to entitle themſelves to the right of exerciſing a joynt power, not onely of diſpoſing the King, but the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome alſo, though the Covenant be contrary to the exerciſe of any joynt power which was ſeverall and diſtinct, before the making thereof; and although the joynt exerciſe of ſuch power be a breach of Covenant; both of us reſpectively be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therby obliged in our ſeverall Vocations mutually to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the rights, priviledges, and Liberties of each Parliament and kingdom, and the exerciſe of ſuch a joynt power, which gives a negative voyce to either Nation towards other, is a manifeſt breach of thoſe Priviledges and Liberties, ſo Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted to be intirely preſerved, and conſequently of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant it ſelfe. And whereas both in their Printed papers to the people, and their diſſent to the Propoſitions ſent lately to the King at the Iſle of <hi>Wyght,</hi> this joynt propriety is ſo much ſtood upon, yet neither is the word <hi>joyntly</hi> nor any other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion which will bear that interpretation ſo much as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Covenant, but the direct contrary, in thoſe words <hi>Bach one in his ſeverall Vocation; Calling; Place, and Intereſt,</hi> which runs through the whole Covenant, and which would have cleared the meaning of it, but therefore they cunningly leave it out, and break off in the midſt of a ſentence, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive the people, who they find too apt to take upon truſt, and to ſuſpect ſtrangers leſſe than there is cauſe.</p>
            <p>For <hi>per fas &amp; nefas,</hi> the deſigne if it will not goe, it muſt be driven, and ſo it is, from one ſtage to another; for whereas formerly the diſpoſe of the Kings perſon was only pretended to, now they are mounted to a higher ſtaire and ſteppe of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment, the empowring of the Crowne; and whereas
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116243:4"/>
the Covenant runs thus: <hi>The preſervation and defence of the Kings perſon, and authority in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They notwithſtanding make a ſtop at <hi>Authority,</hi> and thus our Engliſh ſentences are read with Scotch comma's and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods, and the Covenant made to ſpeake what it never meant, and Covenanters to undertake abſolutely what they promiſe but conditionally, by theſe Scotch Artificers, who make it a noſe of wax, and here in England takes upon them to tell you, That the King and Crowne ſhall have the negative voyce, the regall <hi>Militia,</hi> yea and Court of Wards too, or as good, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſtand with the preſervation and defence of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Kingdomes liberties or not, further then which the Covenant binds not; nay though they ſee apparently all's loſt, if it be ſo, the King being as firme to his principles both Eccleſiaſticall and Civill, as ever, yea and for our better ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, they'l have the Army disbanded in hope the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot eaſily raiſe another, and ſo they may command in chiefe in the North, the Londoners in the South, and the Cavalliers Eaſt and Weſt; and then their owne fleſh and blood, the eleven Members may returne in freedome, honour, and ſafety, and put Mr. <hi>Pellam</hi> in the chaire againe. Thus they doe by us as the Philiſtims did by <hi>Sampſon,</hi> been uſe they cannot binde us, they put out our eyes, and make us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> round in a Mil, leave us as they found us &amp; worſe, beſides the expence of ſo much blood and mony ſince, with our hands in our pockets; that ſo their new brother-hood the Cavalliers may riſe and cut our throats, with whom they are confident of a joynt intereſt both in King and Kingdome.</p>
            <p>When they were pleaſed to ſay, It was prejudiciall to <hi>both Kingdomes,</hi> (for there lies the Emphaſis) for the King, (becauſe they had no minde to him) to goe into <hi>Scotland,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were content they ſhould leave him in <hi>England,</hi> where alſo they'le diſpoſe of him, and have him come to <hi>London,</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116243:5"/>
honour and ſafety (which are comprehenſive tearmes; before any peace be concluded or propoſitions granted, and that too, as the ſafeſt for the Kingdome (I <hi>ſhould ſay both Kingdomes)</hi> under penalty of breach of Covenant, which they uſe now as the Pope in old time was wont to doe his excommunications, <hi>to compaſſe Kingdomes.</hi> And for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>London</hi> they bring a weighty reaſon of ſutable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry to the reſt of their tranſactions. <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament invited him to come thither before the warres break out, as being then the onely meanes to prevent them (and now to renew them) that therefore after ſo much blood and treaſure ſpilt and ſpent, upon that reaſon he muſt come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out condition or ſatisfaction, at his owne election, and be reſtored before His Kingdome be repaired; this is brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love and kind dealing indeed. What will poſterity think of ſuch Covenanters, brethren, and Auxiliaries, who doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe are out of our pay and have forfeited their arreares that thus in their late Papers alarum the whole Kingdom, and ſet their Pay-maſters at defiance, and would now ſel their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their Prince, as they did their Prince to their Party. Beſides that, to pay them were to arme them, till they retract their book: Nor do men uſe to give wages to thoſe they hire, for going up and downe the houſe from roome to roome and rid no worke, when worke is to bee done, as the <hi>Scots</hi> did here in perambulation from Country to Country, and dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the warres neither fought battaile nor ſtormed Towne but <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> but now they make an amends for their idlenes by turning buſie-bodies, they kept their skins whole, and their Army entire to begin, it ſeems, when we had made an end, but beginne when they will, they'le find work for <hi>Tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> all <hi>England</hi> is not of one mind, their Papers are too long for all to read them, and too falſe to be beleeved by all that doe read them, and more there are that ſide with them for faction, then that will ſide with them in fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116243:5"/>
their Countries intereſt, But they give you reaſons, (or at leaſt would ſee me to doe ſo) why the <hi>Militia</hi> muſt bee inherent in the Crowne, and the negative voice in the King. The reaſon of the <hi>Militia</hi> is becauſe of the protection, the Crowne muſt afford to the people, ſo ſayes the King when he means nothing leſſe, and further tell us, That for the Crowne to be diveſted of all power and right of the <hi>Militia is different from their judgements,</hi> a ſtrong reaſon, and impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively ſpoken, enough to have been uttered by the Kings ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voice, and for the regall protection they ſpeake of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt enemies, we have found, and they have ſeen it turned to deſtruction (as ſtill its like to be) and an oath broken on one part, ſets the other at liberty, our government being pactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and our Allegiance according to the nature of but Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, not of ſlaves and vaſſalls, but of Freemen. As the King is made for the people, and not the people for the King, ſo is he firſt bound to the people, and then they to him. But we have now more need of protection againſt falſe brethren then open enemies, which we cannot expect from the King their Country-man, and therefore its better to have the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> in the power of the Parliament, <hi>Englands</hi> abſtract. And as they tell you what their judgement is not, ſo alſo what it is, <hi>viz.</hi> That they thinke the King in his meſſage from <hi>Careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke</hi> Caſtle, hath offered that which ſhould be very ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory in the point of the <hi>Militia.</hi> I wonder not that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents them, being I am confident a childe of their own brame inſtilled into him at Hampton-Court (when they went to ſee how he did) for its perfectly like them, a conſent like the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant (as they make it) meerly an <hi>aliquid nihil.</hi> But what if other men be of other mindes, and have not we cauſe to bee ſo, and to thinke it unſatisfactory<hi>:</hi> for is not the Prince in his capacity as bad as the King? principled by father and mother to begin where he leaves; is not the Parliament put in truſt by the people to provide for their ſecurity; and ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116243:6"/>
they bee ſo baſe as to expoſe poſterity, had our forefathers been ſo ſelfiſh, the Free-men of England might have been like the bondmen in Scotland, where the common people ſpeake broken French.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of the negative voyce is, as they affirme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe regall power and authority is chiefly in making and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacting Lawes, and therefore object, That the new preface takes away the Kings negative voice, and cuts off all royall power and right in Law-making, wherein by the way they play the Sophyſters (being excellent School men in State matters) for when they ſpeake of the <hi>Militia,</hi> which is leſſe concerned <hi>in terminis</hi> in the Coronation oath, which princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally reſpects Civil matters, yet they bring it for a proof as to that, ſaying, That all Kings are obliged by their Coronation oath to protect their Subjects, but as to his negative voice, the excluſion whereof is both the ſubſtance of that oath, and this preamble, they blanch it, taking and leaving as makes for their turnes in Oaths and Covenants, and making at beſt that oath as to the Lawes, ſpeake but the language of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valliers, whoſe interpretation of <hi>only protecting the Laws,</hi> they take up, and decline that of the Parliaments <hi>of confirming and making them,</hi> ſo fully evinced in their Declarations to be the genuine ſenſe thereof, and in right reaſon, and true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction it muſt needs be ſo, That <hi>he ſweares to confirme and grant all ſuch Laws as his people ſhall chooſe</hi> to be obſerved, not <hi>hath choſen:</hi> for firſt, the word <hi>concedis</hi> in that oath were then unneceſſary, the Lawes formerly enacted being already gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by foregoing Kings his predeceſſors, and ſo need no more conceſſion or confirmation, elſe we muſt conclude that all our Lawes dye with the old King, and receive their Being a new by the new Kings conſent. Secondly, hereby the firſt and ſecond clauſe in that interrogatory, viz. <hi>Concedis juſtas leges &amp; permitt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> protegendas,</hi> are confounded, and doe but <hi>idem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6+ letters">
                     <desc>••••••…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Quas vulgus elegerit,</hi> implies only the act of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116243:6"/>
the people in a diſ-junctive ſenſe from the act or conſent of the King, but Laws already made have more then <hi>Quas vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus elegerit</hi> in them, they have alſo the Royall conſent too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that that phraſe cannot mean thoſe Laws wherein the act and conſent of the King is already involved. But though the Scots Commiſſioners approve not of it to be the meaning of that Oath, yet they affirme it undeniably as a poſition of their owne, <hi>That regall power is chiefly in making and enacting Laws; that and protection being of the eſſence of Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scots ſay its eſſentiall to the King to make Laws, the Preamble to the Propoſitions ſayes ſo too, That it's the duty of his office, yet they that affirme that, oppoſe this, ſo that there muſt needs be ſome great miſ-underſtanding, for there is no difference, which is this. The Scots when they ſay. It is eſſentiall to the King to make Laws, ſpeake by a figure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to their dialect, that is, <hi>They ſpeake one thing, when they meane another</hi> (you may finde the name of it in <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> his politicks) intending thereby, That it is eſſentiall to him <hi>not to make Lawes,</hi> elegantly aſſerting the negative (which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for) in the affirmative. (For they ſpeake all in the plurall number <hi>Kings and Kingdomes,</hi> nothing but joynt intereſts and equall juriſdiction, municipall lawes are out of doores.) And let it be granted that it is a principall part of even our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall authority to make and enact Lawes, for the Coronation oath ſaith as much, <hi>That he is to confirme and grant ſuch Lawes as his people ſhall preſent;</hi> ſo alſo ſayes this Preamble to the Propoſitions, and what get they by it? why then ſay they to take away the Kings negative voyce is to cut off all power and right in making Lawes; nothing leſſe, this is a meer <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> for to make him that he cannot but make them, is that to make him that hee cannot make them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There are ſomethings that God himſelfe cannot but doe, (which is as well his perfection and power (not imperfection and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency) as thoſe things he can chuſe to doe) and does that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116243:7"/>
therefore imply that he cannot doe what he cannot but do? Things eſſentiall are not arbitrary but neceſſary, ſo is <hi>mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lawes</hi> to the Office of a King, but ſo is not his <hi>not mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them:</hi> It ſeemes by the <hi>Scots</hi> creed tranſlated into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> (for they are not of this faith, at leaſt not of this practice at home) nothing's royall but what's arbitrary, a poſition fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> to maintaine, then Chriſtians and men of erudition, that ſo preferres will to reaſon, and the will of one man lapſ'd and relapſ'd to the reaſon of a State, making that which is the worſt to rule by, the ſole or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall rule of all rule and Government. They are now at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd to that confidence as after all that's done and ſuffered by the Parliament and Kingdome for an eſtabliſhment of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and ſafety, openly to advocate it for the King againſt theſe, (preferring their intereſt which is againſt them, above their Covenant which is for them) notwithſtanding the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion they made to the contrary and the money, <hi>viz.</hi> 600000. <hi>li.</hi> 100000. <hi>li.</hi> at their comming in, 200000. <hi>li.</hi> at their going out. 250000. <hi>li.</hi> for coales at <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi> 50000. <hi>li.</hi> when they lay before <hi>Hereford,</hi> are ſuch another ſumme when they lay before <hi>Newarke,</hi> beſides free-quarter, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bitrary aſſeſements, and exactions; which in computation during their long ſtay to little purpoſe amounted to above as much more. They have had for their ſeeming ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe thereunto. And now all the courteſie we muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect is onely this, for they are their owne words. <hi>It is not our deſire that Monarchy ſhould be at the abſolute height of an arbitrary and tyrannicall power.</hi> Implying an allowance or content of ſome, yea, a great deale of arbitrary and tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Monarchicall power, and for this it ſeems they contend, the whilſt they go about to erect theſe two Pillars of it in the Crown, <hi>a Negative voyce and a Regall Militia,</hi> and indeed the Crowne having them, what can hinder it of an arbitrary ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall power even to the height thereof, if he that weares
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116243:7"/>
it be ſo diſpoſed, for by the power of the one the people can have no Lawes but what heele grant them, and by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the other they are never the better for them, nor ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of them when they have them; the Militia inveſting the King with a negative power of undoing at pleaſure what he of curteſie hath done or granted to them, and ſo his people are ſtript of all power or righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, both to get or keepe what's for their weale or their poſterities, and all rendered at the Kings will and mercy and that by Law and Allegiance too, then which I doe not well underſtand how there can be a more abſolute height of Monarchicall arbitrary tiranny, then by pretended Law and right to have it in his power to doe what he will, (abſolute perſian) for ſo his will by law gives law to all lawes and the ſubjects benefit in his meere beneficence.</p>
            <p>For if the Subject deſire good lawes hee may ſtop their mouths and tell them that by Law he may deny them, or if he be in a good mind and grant them, and after change and be deſirous either to unmake them or to breake them (which yet the <hi>Medes</hi> could not doe) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s what's more changeable then the will of a King (whether he be <hi>Englands</hi> or <hi>Iſraels Solomon)</hi> ſubject to alteration upon every puffe of paſſion, or trade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind of flattery <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And then if the Subject take armes for defence of their Lawes he ſoiles them at that guard too, and and tells them by Law the Militia is his not theirs; And if they reply but he is to uſe it for the publique weale, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers them, I may chuſe by my negative voyce, and thus the poore Engliſh-man by Scotch ſophiſtry is toſt from poſt to pillar voide of all certainty and ſtability, and is meerly <hi>ad placitum</hi> in ſubſtance, though in ſhadow a freeman<hi>:</hi> theſe are no Levellers, theſe are Mountainers, high landers: but how can wee expect better when ſtrangers and men of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary intereſt to us, are our Legiſ-lators and take upon them the higheſt Office of judicatory in this Kingdome next to making Lawes (which they ſay is the Kings, and therefore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116243:8"/>
they will not take that from him.) <hi>viz.</hi> to interpret our Lawes and Liberties, and ſo by a writ of alienation we are ſhared out 'twixt him and them, he to make, and they to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret, and thus the Engliſh Parliament betwixt two ſtooles falls to the ground, and becomes a meere nullity, and yet the Scots Commiſſioners (the renewers of our miſeries) play the Courtiers, and tell you in Latine inſtead of Engliſh, that they profeſſe <hi>ignorantiam facti</hi> &amp; <hi>juris alieni,</hi> but their words and actions agree as did their words and ſwords, promiſe much and doe nothing.</p>
            <p>Further to make good theſe their aſſertions touching the Kings Right to the Militia, and a Negative voyce, they prove it by the Scepter and Sword, which they ſay are badges of thoſe powers to be in the King, it may be ſo in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but in <hi>England</hi> they ſignifie not the power of creation (ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally not of annihilation of Laws) but of execution of civill and penall Juſtice, elſe by this reaſon the Mayor of a Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, whoſe badges in proportion import the ſame things, ſhould have a Negative voyce, and be a Law-maker (or law-refuſer) who indeed is the Laws Miniſter, and ſo is the King, the fountain of <hi>Juſtice</hi> not of <hi>Laws.</hi> But to ſhew how incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent and irrationall it is for the King of <hi>England</hi> to have a Negative voyce (for, for the impertinencies of other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inſtanced by them, there need no other anſwer, but that we neither give nor take Laws from any but our ſelves)t may appear by theſe following conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>By the Kings not ſitting in Parliament to debate and conſult Lawes, nor are they at all offered him by the Parliament to conſider of, but only to conſent unto, which yet are tranſmitted from one of the Houſes to the other as well to conſult, as conſent to, ſhewing thereby that he hath no ſhare in the conſultory part of them (for that it belongs only to the people in Parliament to diſcerne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult their owne good) but he comes only at the time of enacting, bringing his royall authority with him, as it were to ſet the ſeal therof to the Indenture already prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the people, for the King is head of the Parliament (as of the people) in regard of his authority, not in regard of his reaſon and judgement, as if it were</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116243:8"/>
               <hi>oppoſed to the reaſon and judgement of both Houſes (which is the reaſon both of King and Kingdome) and therefore doe they as conſult, ſo interpret Laws with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, ſuppoſing him to be a perſon repleniſhed with honour and royall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, not skill'd in Lawes, nor to receive information either of law or counſell in Parliamentary affaires from any, ſaving from the ſupreme Court, and higheſt Councell of the King and Kingdome, which admits of no counterpoiſe, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with all, above all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Either the choice of the people in Parliament, is to be the ground and rule of the Kings aſſent, or nothing but his pleaſure, &amp; ſo all Bills though never ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for publique good and preſervation, and after never ſo much paines and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation of both Houſes may be voided, and ſo they made meer cyphers, and we brought to that paſſe, as either to have no Lawes, or ſuch as come onely and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from the King (who oft is a man of pleaſure, and little ſeen in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke affaires to be able to judge) and ſo the Kingdomes great Councell muſt bee ſubordinated either to his meer will (and then what difference between a free Monarchy, and an abſolute, ſaving that the one rules without counſell, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt it) or at the beſt but to a cabinet councell, conſiſting commonly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f men of perſonall intereſts, but certainly of no publick truſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>By the practice of requiring the royall aſſent even unto thoſe very acts of Subſidies which are granted to himſelfe, and for his owne uſe, which it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed he will accept of, and yet</hi> Honoris gratia, <hi>his royall aſſent is asked and contributed thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, from the Scots owne poſition, which is this, <hi>That regall power and authority is chiefly in making and enacting Lawes, and in protecting and defending their ſubjects, which are of the very eſſence and Being of all Kings.</hi> Whence I argue, that then he hath a negative power in <hi>neither</hi> no more in the one then in the other, but as he is not to deny pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to his people, ſo nor Lawes, for (as aforeſaid) things eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall are neceſſary, theſe then being ſo to the office of a King, hee is not arbitrary in their diſpenſation, but as he muſt doe the one, <hi>viz</hi> protect not, deſtroy his people, ſo alſo the other, <hi>viz.</hi> conſent not, diſſent to their Lawes, for to conſent is either a meere act of his will and pleaſure, and then not eſſentiall to his place, or the iſſue of his duty, and then not of his meere will, as it is of a Judge to do juſtice, and therefore cannot (that is ought not) to be denyed, this their owne poſition, whereupon they would build the negative voyce, quite deſtroyes it and concludes both againſt it and them.</p>
            <p>In a word, the Fundamentall Law of the Land, is a ſetling
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116243:9"/>
of Government, ſo as that it may be adminiſtred, with honour and ſafety, and therefore the people firſt conſult their own ſafety and welfare in Parliament, and then the King, who is to be intruſted with it, is to give an honourable confirmation to it, and ſo to put an Impreſſe of Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty and Royall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority upon it. The Legiſlative power in <hi>England</hi> is in the hands of the ſupreme Government, not Governour, here the people like Freemen offers Laws to be enacted, doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them ſo, nor ought to be denyed them. The King is to give life to ſuch Acts and things as tend to publique good and protection, which Acts depend not upon his pleaſure, but though they are to receive their greater vigour from him, yet are they not to be ſuſpended at pleaſure by him, for that which at firſt was intended by the Kingdoms for an honourable way of ſubſiſtence and adminiſtration muſt not be wreſted contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the nature of this polity and Inſtitution, inſomuch as if the King in his perſon decline his duty, the King in his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to performe it; Safety and Beeing, is to be preferred to Honour and Well-being, and Reallities to Formes, which are uſefull, if not hurtfull, Good Hand-maids, but bad Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, being but Honourable Accidents, not Eſſences, like beauty to the face, or Jewels to the Crown, which, though they be pawn'd, its not eſſentially impair'd; Civill ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may undo us as well as Eccleſiaſticall, which commonly goe together, and one of them oft times is the puniſhment of the other; Civill diſſentions, Prerogative Wars, and <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burian</hi> Altars began at once. <hi>The peoples hearts were not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,</hi> was of old the ſin of many ages, and the cauſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny judgements, <hi>God grant it be not ſo with Englands Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Janua. 29. 1647.</p>
            <p>Imprimatur <hi>Gilbert Mabbot.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
